What have you learned about AI from
your trip to China and thinking about
China, speaking to Chinese
people, whether they're technologists or
otherwise? Like, what have you learned
during or since that trip?
>> Back in March, before my book was
published in the US,
I went to China because the Chinese are
faster at everything, including
publishing books.
And uh my publisher brought me out there
and basically, you know, took me around
four cities, eight days, meeting with AI
leaders both in academia and big
companies like Huawei and Hikvision and
Ant Group.
And the thing which was surprising
was the extent to which people brought
up the issue of AI safety.
And I say that was surprising because my
friends who had done AI policy in the
Biden administration
had primed me to expect that there would
be no mention of safety in China, that
they basically didn't care about it,
that
you know, the muscle memory that we have
in the West
of technology being dangerous, you know,
the atom bomb experience, the Cuban
missile crisis,
our ambivalence about technology is not
shared in China, where their idea of
catastrophe is sort of like, you know,
the Cultural Revolution, it's some
political thing that goes wrong. And
conversely, technology has been part of
their amazing growth story in the last
25 years, which they are rightly proud
of and delighted by. So, they love
technology, right? So,
when the Biden team tried to meet with
the Chinese and talk about AI safety,
they got nowhere and they decided it was
impossible to even talk to them about
some sort of non-proliferation treaty
for AI.
But when I went there, I found they did
talk about safety kind of unprompted.
And this led me down this track of
arguing over the last couple of months
that the door is actually open
to a dialogue with China
about preventing bad guys doing bad
stuff
with AI.
Because they don't want the internet to
be crashed by some cyber hacker who has
the tool.
They don't want bio weapons, they don't
want chemical weapons, they want none of
that. They love regulating the internet,
right? So we have a shared interest with
the Chinese in preventing this
proliferation of risk
from going nuts.
And as I thought about it, you know, the
kind of Cold War analogy
came to seem more and more opposite,
right? So if you look back at the story
of nuclear weapons, there were two kinds
of danger.
First danger is you have a nuclear war
between the Soviet Union and the United
States.
But that was contained by balance.
Two superpowers, they both have the
weaponry.
They have mutually assured destruction,
so there's no war.
Then there's another kind of risk, which
is that other random rogues, whether
it's criminals, terrorists, rogue
states,
get the stuff and they do bad stuff, and
it's much harder to deter that because
it's a multipolar game.
And so deterrence doesn't work so
elegantly.
And so the way it was dealt with in the
Cold War was that in 1956 there was the
agreement on the International Atomic
Energy Agency.
And in 1968 the Non-Proliferation Treaty
kind of enforced compliance with the
IAEA
such that you could get civilian nuclear
power
if you were a non-nuclear state, but you
had to submit to the rules and be
inspected and show that you were not
using
the enriched nuclear material to build a
weapon, right?
And so I think the same analogy could be
applied to AI. We're going to have
parity roughly with China. We'll both
have powerful AI. Hopefully deterrence
prevents war breaking out.
But at the same time, we don't want open
weight models that can be freely
downloaded by anybody who wants to fall
into the hands of criminals and
terrorists
who can then use it to hold us hostage.
And we have a joint interest in that.
And you know, when my friends from the
Biden team or even from the current
administration say,
"Well, you can't talk to China about
safety. They don't care." I say, "That's
not true." And they say, "But it's
really hard. They don't stick by their
commitments." And I go, "You think
Nikita Khrushchev in [snorts] the Soviet
Union was easy to negotiate with? He was
the guy who put missiles in Cuba and
went to the UN and banged his shoe on
the table and said, "We will bury you."
I mean, he was a tough guy to talk to,
but we did talk to him and we got the
non-proliferation treaty agreed.
And I think we need to do the same thing
again now.
>> Where do you stand on
your thinking about chip export?
>> So, when the chip export controls were
announced,
which was October of 2022, right before
ChatGPT,
I supported those controls quite loudly.
I wrote a very long piece in the
Washington Post saying that if we could
stop China getting frontier models by
depriving them of frontier chips,
I was all in favor of that because of
the strategic advantage for the US. I
mean, I work at the Council on Foreign
Relations.
We do geopolitics and national security
all day long.
And I'm all in favor of US power.
But I have to say that, you know, 3 and
1/2 years later,
we haven't actually achieved that
enormous advantage over China in terms
of the models. Based on the best
studies, we're kind of 8 months ahead in
terms of where the frontier model is,
like our frontier model versus their
frontier model.
And then if you adjust for the speed
with which the model gets turned into an
application,
probably that gap shrinks, and it may
even be nonexistent.
So, however you slice that, the basic
bottom line is we both have strong
models, and the chip export controls
have not delivered what I hoped would be
the big advantage.
And so, I'm not against keeping the
controls on
if we think that maybe as the compute
demands of bigger and bigger models
bite,
the chip controls will bite more, and
maybe we get a bigger advantage next
year or something.
But I don't want the chip controls to
get in the way of discussion with the
Chinese about where we have a shared
interest,
which is in controlling open weight
models
and preventing the bad stuff falling
into the hands of the bad guys.
I would prioritize
collaboration with China, and if that
meant, you know, loosening up a little
bit on the export controls, I would be
okay with that.